Watch out! I'm about to blow your mind, bro. Businesses want you to buy stuff.
I know. This is shocking news. But perhaps even more shocking is that online,
businesses drive to get you to open your wallets can often involve quite a bit of subterfuge known
as dark patterns. Surprisingly, this isn't the name of a metal band. Rather, it's a tactic
designed to influence you somehow, usually into buying a product or service you might not really
want to sign up for incessant marketing emails or simply to stop you from doing something the
business may not want you to do. And dark patterns aren't one size fits all. Just like a Stephen
King monster, a dark pattern can take many forms. One classic example is how hard it often is to
find a phone number to talk to a real human being when you need customer service. Websites often
instead direct you to fill out a form or text chat with a representative. If a phone number
even exists, it's often buried in a subtle location that you have to click multiple links to find.
A related tactic is how hard some services make it to close your account.
You've probably seen how companies will bury the unsubscribe link on an email at the bottom in
tiny font. But this is small potatoes compared to trying to straight up cancel a membership.
Typically, bringing up a settings menu and clicking close your account isn't good enough.
Sites will either entice you to stay with a massive in your face offer to prevent you from
canceling a subscription with the actual cancel link presented in a much smaller size. Or they'll
make it insanely hard to find the actual delete your account button. Amazon is notorious for this,
and many other things. The latter is a good example of what designers call a roach motel.
Easy to sign up for an account and get in, but hard to leave. And while you might not end up dead,
like an actual roach, it makes life super annoying. And may even result in a recurring charge in
your card if you don't deactivate your account in time. But even if burying the link you actually
want to click isn't a tactic a certain company is employing, there are other gotchas to watch out for.
One is how these sites will use UI elements to nudge the user in a certain direction.
For example, making a buy tokens or keep my subscription button a bright color,
or at least a color the user recognizes from other parts of the service.
This can also be done in a less subtle way, called Confirm Shaming.
Wait, are we on Twitter? You see this a lot when you visit a retailer or travel site,
and get a pop-up to sign up for a newsletter promising discounts and other exclusive offers.
If you're not interested in getting emails, bam, you can't just click on an X button,
or a button that says close. Instead, you have to click a small link, saying something to the
effective, no thanks, I'd rather pay full price, or some other condescending nonsense.
But possibly the worst form of Dark Pattern is the one that actively requires you to click an
extra button to opt out of something. This can be anything from how tedious some sites make it to
reject unnecessary cookies. Yes, to having a box to install some unwanted antivirus program,
or unwanted toolbar pre-checked for you when you're trying to install something else
completely unrelated. By the time you've clicked through reflexively, congratulations!
You're now the proud owner of a trip protection package, and probably some malware.
Of course, these aren't the only kinds of dark patterns floating around out there,
so while it's a pain, be sure to take a few extra seconds to read before you click.
You don't want to end up in a position where you agree to have your robot vacuum
suck up all your loose change and hold it ransom. It happened to me.
Speaking of loose change, save yours by getting your books in order with our sponsor,
FreshBooks. They're an invoicing and accounting solution that's built for owners and their
clients. FreshBooks states that the average user saves 46 hours a month and gets paid 18 days
faster while increasing their ROI by 11 times using FreshBooks. FreshBooks is hugely beneficial for
freelancers and small business owners who don't have time to waste on invoicing, accounting,
and payment processing. Over 3,000 business owners have rated it an average of 4.5 out of five
stars on GitHub. It's super easy to get up and running, and with award-winning support,
you're never alone. Try FreshBooks free for 30 days, no credit card required.
Go to FreshBooks.com slash TechQuickie and enter TechQuickie in the how did you hear about
a section? Because you got to be honest. Hey, thanks for watching guys. Like the video,
dislike the video, check out our other videos, comment with video suggestions. It's all about
videos here on the YouTube video channel TechQuickie. Hey, why don't you subscribe and follow?
That's an idea.